Okay, well, welcome back to another problem session.
It's great to see everybody's smiling faces again.
Right, so today we're going to continue our discussion of graph theory problems,
this time focusing on, well, a little bit of this, a little bit
of that, some shortest path problems, all-pairs shortest path,
and then a modification of the Dijkstra algorithm to finish us off for the day.
So, as always, we'll go through our problem session problems in order
for no reason other than that's the way they were presented to me.
And I think roughly isomorphic to how most of the homeworks in this class go anyway.
But in any event, let's get started here. So, in problem session problem
7-1 here, as always, our first problem is sort of a warm-up to make sure
that we understand the problem. We understand all these
sort of definitions, techniques that we use in 6.006.
Today, we're going to go over Dijkstra's algorithm.
So, if you all recall, Dijkstra's algorithm is a technique for
computing shortest path from a single source to your rest of your graph.
There's about a million different ways to explain, understand Dijkstra's
algorithm. So, I'll undoubtedly revert upon the one that I remember,
which is probably not the one that Jason just
covered in lecture, but we'll make it work.
And, of course, if there are any questions, we'll address those along the way here.
I'm going to switch to it. This is a piece
of chalk that isn't an eighth of an inch.
And get started.
Right. So, in problem 1-A of our homework here, we were
asked to run Dijkstra's algorithm from vertex S here.
By the way, just sort of a standard terminology in graph theory that I
think we'll see a lot in the homework is we typically use S for the sort
of starting point of a path or sometimes the source if we're talking
about network flows, but I don't think we do those in this class.
And then T is usually the starting point. So, we're going to start with the
starting point of a path, and then we're going to start with the source.
And then D is usually the destination.
Why T, you might ask? Because
it's the letter after S.
Right. So, our first task here is to compute the single
source shortest path from S to everything else in our graph.
Initially, this looks painful, but it's not.
So, you're going to forgive me.
I'm going to write a sort of shorthand version of Dijkstra's algorithm because I'm talking to you as I solve this problem,
which, of course, would be much more annoying for you guys to do on paper.
But that's life in the city. So, there. That's my, in the words
of Britney Spears, it's my prerogative as your instructor here.
Okay. So, in Dijkstra's algorithm, what do we do? We initially
label all of our vertices as having distance infinity to the source,
and we insert them into our priority Q, except for one vertex, which, of course, is our source vertex.
And he or she has distance zero for an obvious reason, which is that if my path starts at the source,
it has distance zero. So, that's my priority.
So, that's my priority. So, as our shorthand...
What was that? Do
I want to use red?
Yes, of course I do.
But it's this fat chalk, man.
Okay.
Zero. I can make this work.
Okay. So, our convention for today is going to be if a
vertex does not have a label on it, it is distance infinity.
Okay?
So, what does Dijkstra's algorithm do?
Dijkstra's algorithm grabs... the closest
vertex that I haven't yet processed,
and closest in terms of the distance value that I've stored at that vertex,
and then updates all of its neighbors using sort of a triangle
inequality style construction. So, let's see what that looks like.
So, so far, everything is distance infinity away, except
for one vertex, which is vertex S, which is distance zero.
So, obviously, that should be our first iteration of Dijkstra's algorithm.
And now, what vertex S is going to do is look at all of S's neighbors and update them using the same algorithm.
So, I'm going to update them using the triangle inequality.
And if they're closer by having a path through S to the neighbor,
then I update the distance. And if it's not, then I don't.
In this case, everything is infinity.
So, it's pretty clear that I should route my path through S, because any distance less than infinity is smaller than infinity.
So, in particular, notice that there's an edge of length eight from S to A.
So, now, rather than being distance infinity away, I can
see that vertex A is really distance eight away. Oh, this
The kind of nice thing about the way Dijkstra's algorithm works, which I guess is a little bit implicit
in the construction we saw yesterday, but that's OK, is that once
I visit a vertex, I never touch it again. It gets frozen in time.
In distance, I suppose. But in any event, what that means, I'm
going to put a little box around it, meaning I'm done with this guy.
He's no longer in my queue. OK. Hopefully, our pictorial system
makes some sense here. Again, on your homework problem, you
actually have to write this stuff out. And I'm sorry, that sucks.
But I don't have to because I'm talking to you all today. OK.
So remember Dijkstra's algorithm. We're going to look at our list
of vertices we haven't seen yet. So it's everything except for s.
Find the one that's closest and process that one next. So in this case,
that's the 7 here. OK. So let's take a look. What are the neighbors of 7?
Well, I've got s and that's oh, and d here. OK. So first of all, let's
take a look at s. Obviously, if I have a path that goes through c,
back through this vertical edge to s, that path will have length
8, right? 7 plus 1. 8 is bigger than 0. So I do not update s.
But we actually already knew that because s was frozen here. So I didn't
even have to look at that edge. I could have removed it if I wanted to. OK.
But there's another edge coming out of c, which is pointing toward d that
has length 4. 7 plus 4 is, wait for it, 11. And that's less than infinity.
So I update d's distance to 11. And I don't think I've managed to
make a mistake yet. OK. So now we looked at all the edges out of c.
And c is frozen. And we move on. OK. Next, let's see. Among our vertices,
we have infinity, 8 and 11. So the smallest of those three numbers is 8.
And we're going to update all of the neighbors of the
8. Which thankfully, although this graph looks big,
they had some mercy on your section instructor today. And really,
there aren't that many edges. So this isn't too hard to process.
But here's the thing. There's an edge of length 0
from a to d here. I can get to the a in 8 units.
So I can also get to the d in 8 units by traversing that edge. 8 is
less than 11. That's good news. Do I want to erase it or scratch it out?
What's going to be better? No. I'll scratch it out just
to be missed. OK. So now d is a distance 8 from vertex s.
And I believe that's all the edges out of a.
So a is set. OK. This fun or what? So now we look at all the edges out
of, well, oh, sorry. We step back and we look at all of our vertices.
We find the closest one. That's d. And now we've got to update
all of d's neighbors. So thankfully, all the remaining vertices
have distance infinity. So what do we know? There's an edge of length
1 here. So we get a 9. There's an edge of length 2. So I get a 10.
And I believe those are all the outgoing edges from d. And now d is
set. I'm going to start moving faster because this is hella boring. OK.
Now the next closest edge is the 9. Notice that the 9 only, or
rather b, I suppose, is the vertex, which is currently at distance 9.
It only has one neighbor that hasn't yet been processed,
which is e. So we know that that's 9 to 11, 12 distance away.
I'm going to check my scrap paper and make sure I haven't made any
mistakes yet. 7, 8. Cool. OK. So now our next closest vertex is vertex h,
which is distance 10. And aha, if I traverse the edge
upward from h to e, I can get a path of length 11. And 11.
According to most mathematicians, is less than
12. And hence, we should update the value here.
In addition to that, there is an edge of length 2 out of h pointing
into g. 10 plus 2 is 12. And I believe that's it. Getting there. OK.
So the next closest vertex is e. e
has no outgoing edges. So e is all set.
After that, we've got g. g has an outgoing edge. And g has an outgoing
edge of length 1 into d. 12 plus 1 is 13, which is larger than 8.
So we don't update. And similarly, 12 plus 0 is bigger than 7.
So we don't update. But again, the edges that point into vertices
that we've already processed, we really don't have to even
consider just by the way that Dijkstra's algorithm works.
Notice that if there were a negative weight edge, we're going
to come back to, then that assumption will be problematic.
So the takeaway here is that this guy is frozen in
stone. And now, notice that our q is actually empty.
Yeah, so depending on how we set up our, well, it's not empty.
But it only contains one vertex. And it's at distance infinity.
Infinity plus 0 is still infinity. So that's this guy's distance here. And
now our q is empty. Sorry. OK, so I believe I managed to do that right.
Excellent. So the problem asks for two things. It asks for the single
source shortest path distance. It also asks for the traversal order,
which I forgot to do while I was doing this problem. But you could
retrace it pretty easily. OK, so that's part A. Then in part B,
they say change the weight of the edge from g to c to minus 6. So we
have g to c. And now, instead of 0, we're going to make it minus 6.
And the question is, if I ran Dijkstra's algorithm, essentially,
what would break? And I think it's pretty easy to eyeball.
Remember that g was essentially the last interesting vertex that we
touched in our algorithm here. The only one that we looked at was f.
And so this outgoing edge from g actually wouldn't even be seen by Dijkstra's
algorithm, thankfully, until we've touched all these other vertices
in an identical fashion to our previous traversal. And
then we finally get to g. And now what's going to happen?
Well, if I have this edge of length negative 6, what's 12 minus 6?
That's 6. And notice that that's less than 7, which is the label.
That's the label of vertex c. But that breaks our assumption, which
is that as soon as I visit a vertex, I never have to touch it again.
Because now I've identified a path through g back to c that has a
smaller distance than the path that c had when it was visited in the q.
So somehow spiritually, I should add c back to the q. But that's against
the rules in Dijkstra's algorithm. So for instance, if I did that, I
would have to convince myself that the runtime
doesn't explode and this algorithm terminates,
which could be a problem if you have a negative weight cycle.
Thankfully, we have algorithms for detecting negative weight
cycles, but that's a different matter. OK, so I think this is pretty
straightforward. It's just essentially asking you to walk through Dijkstra's
algorithm, make sure you understand what's going on. Any questions about
that one? Cool, I think this is one of the easier problem sessions.
So we'll finish early. Except I always say that. I talk too
much. Sorry. Not sorry. OK, so right. So in problem 7-2.
This is an extension of a problem that we considered, I believe,
two problem sessions ago. And it looks something like this.
I'm going to go back into my notes. So remember, in two problem
sessions ago, we defined the radius of a graph for an unweighted graph.
We came up with an algorithm for computing
it and approximating it, all that good stuff.
Now in this problem, we're going to do basically
the same thing. But now we're on a weighted graph.
So in particular, we're going to define a
quantity. This is problem 2. Called weighted.
Eccentricity.
Which is associated to a vertex in a weighted graph. And it looks
like this. So the weighted eccentricity associated to vertex u
is equal to the max over all vertices in my graph
of the shortest path distance from u to that vertex.
Again, hopefully our audience will catch if I accidently, I'm going
to do this. I'm going to finally swap the argument to shortest path.
I'm used to thinking of that as symmetric. But it's not because our
graphs are directed. Actually, in this problem, I don't think the graph is
directed. So I forget. It's directed. OK.
Good. Yeah. Then good. I'll try to be accurate.
OK. And just like the problem we had two problem sessions
ago, so the eccentricity is associated with a vertex.
It's sort of like the distance to the farthest away thing in my
graph. And now the radius of my graph tries to find the most,
the most vertical distance. So I'm going to write it in the middle
of my graph. And now the radius of my graph tries to find the most,
because I can't find the most vertical distance. So my graph tries to find
the most central vertex, which is the minimizer of weighted eccentricity.
And we call that the weighted radius.
And so the weighted radius is a measurement which is
associated not with the vertex, but rather with the graph.
And it's equal to the min over all possible vertices u, of the
weighted eccentricity of u. And so the problem here is that we're
given a weighted directed graph with no negative weight cycle. So
it may have negative weights, but they can't have a negative cycle.
And the question, I touched my face. The question is, what is the, can I
find the radius of my graph in time that looks like order mod v, v cubed?
OK. Now, if you recall from our previous problem session when
we considered computing the radius of a graph, what did we do?
Well, we tried to come up with a clever algorithm. And then
we realized that that was actually kind of unnecessary.
That it turned out that the kind of brain dead thing where you just
look at the definitions and just make it work was actually good enough.
And that actually turns out to be the case here. This is a good reminder
for us all that, before we're going to do this, we're going to do this.
And we're going to do this. We're going to do this. We're going to do this.
We're going to do this. We're going to do this. We're going to do this.
We're going to do this. We're going to do this. And
before we go crazy, 6.006 is a fun algorithms class.
We get to learn about cute references to TV shows and
all that. Before we go crazy with that, of course,
if there's an obvious algorithm staring us in
the face to solve a given algorithms problem,
we should try that first before we try something more clever. And
indeed, in this case, that works. So what are the sort of ingredients
that we need to compute the radius? Well, the radius is the minimum
eccentricity. So what would be the smartest? Or the simplest thing to do, rather,
would be compute the eccentricity for every vertex and take the
smallest. How do I compute the eccentricity for every vertex?
Well, I have to have the max distance away from that vertex. So what
would be a simple thing to do would be to compute distances between all
the possible vertices. And conveniently, in lecture some day or
another, I'm a little confused about the time ordering of this class
because of the way we're filming it. We covered an algorithm
that computes the distance between every pair of vertices.
And that's called Johnson's algorithm. So if we were to do a totally
brain-dead version of solving this problem, maybe for convenience,
the first thing we do is compute delta uv for every possible uv
pair. And because our graph doesn't have a negative weight cycle,
we can do that with Johnson's algorithm. So step one is to use Johnson's
algorithm for all pairs, short, and long. So we're going to do that.
So step one is to use Johnson's algorithm for all pairs short, and long.
So step two is to use Johnson's algorithm for all pairs short, and long.
So step three is to use Johnson's algorithm for all pairs short,
and long. And I'll refer you guys to lecture for how to do that.
But the important thing is the runtime of this step of our
algorithm. So Johnson's algorithm, generically speaking,
has ve plus v squared log v. Hopefully, I got that
right, runtime. And what do we know about our problem?
Well, I believe we're given that the graph is connected.
And so one thing that we can do is notice that e is upper bounded
by v squared. I guess even if it's not connected, I'm sorry,
that was a dumb thing to say. Just generically speaking, our graph
is simple. So we know that e at most is, I guess, 2v squared,
which means that this term is upper bounded by v cubed. So we have v cubed
plus order v squared log v. So at the end of the day, the first term wins.
And we have that this is v cubed time. Notice that we're given that
budget in the statement of our problem. So this is perfectly fine.
In other words, this is a long-winded way of saying it's kosher to
compute all pairs shortest paths in the constraints of our problem here.
So that's convenient because now in step 2, well, maybe now we just
keep, we do the Toucan-Sam approach again. We follow our noses.
And well, now that we have our pairwise distances,
we can now compute the eccentricity for every vertex.
So we can compute the eccentricity for all u just directly. Of
course, in your homework, you should write out what that means.
But here, directly just means that for every u, I loop
over every v. And I take whatever value is biggest.
So notice that I have two loops, one over u, one over v. So this is
order mod v squared time. So already, the first term is dominating here.
So that's a good thing, I guess. And then finally. We have to take the
smallest eccentricity of any u, which just requires one more for loop.
So this time, I for loop over this array. And I just take the smallest
value. So this is just one for loop. So that takes order v time.
And we're done. So that's our technique for computing the radius. And
notice that all I did was translate the definition into an algorithm.
I didn't do anything. I wasn't really smart in this problem at
all. And then we should really quickly double check our runtime.
So step one takes v cubed time. Step two takes v squared time. Step three
takes v time. So I add them all together. And of course, the v cubed wins.
And that is what was given in our problem as our budget. OK, so I think
the first two problems in this problem session are fairly straightforward.
Are there any questions so far? I'm talking fast.
Cool. All right, so now we're going to move on
to problem three involving Atmus Kevardine, who is probably playing
the Gunger games. Unger games. That was close. Sorry, under whatever.
You get the point. Yeah, so before I get carried away trying to read Jason's
jokes here, what's going on in this problem? So this is problem three.
There's an underground sewer network. I suppose
we also could have written this problem about MIT.
There's all kinds of crazy underground tunnels here. I
remember when I was looking at MIT as a potential undergrad,
they had us schlepping around the tunnels. And I thought they were
very dirty. And I didn't get the point. So I went to Stanford.
But in any event, right, so what I'm given is a map.
And this thing has n bidirectional pipes.
I'm not going to write it down. But the problem tells you that
they're all connected. You can get from your source to your target
moving through the pipes. And right,
and they're connected at junctions.
But at every junction, there's less than or equal to 4 things. There
are things that come together. So just like in our last problem session,
every time you see a phrase like that, it's like screaming
out, there's a degree bound hiding inside of your graph.
And moreover, every junction is reachable from every other junction, I
believe. OK. In addition to this, we're given a positive integer length
for each pipe. So it's starting to smell like a shortest path problem. But
is it? That's our question. But just to make things a little bit worse,
Atnas Keverdine here is trying to escape through
the pipes. And she doesn't want to be detected.
And in particular, there exists junctions with motion
sensors. And apparently, Atnas's Intel is pretty good here.
And she knows which of the junctions in her pipe network actually
have motion sensors that can detect people moving around. OK.
Now, what this problem is asking her to do is to say,
maybe apparently she knows where the motion sensors are.
But maybe she doesn't know if they're like, what kind of brand they
are. You know? A Microsoft sensor or an Apple sensor or something.
And of course, the sensors have different ranges. So Atnas Keverdine
here, she wants to be as conservative as possible when she traverses
this pipe network. In particular, what we're looking for, what she wants,
is in n log n time here, find the path that maximizes the distance.
This is the distance to the sensors.
So hopefully, this problem makes sense. So we've got some grid graph.
Well, not necessarily a grid graph, but a bunch of vertices of valence 4,
maybe something like that. It makes sense. She's living in a
city somewhere. And she has some source that she's starting at,
some destination she wants to go. And then a few of these
vertices, which are marked as having motion sensors at them.
And rather than giving you a radius or something like that, instead,
what we're saying is that she wants to go from the source to the target.
She's willing to walk a long distance. The length of the
path doesn't matter. What matters is that she never wants
to get closer to any motion sensor. Maybe there's a second one like here.
Then she has to. OK? So in this case, I guess if I were to eyeball it,
looks like you can't do better than one edge, right? So she
would go like that. And of course, in an extreme scenario,
it might be the case that there's a sensor at every junction, in
which case she's hosed. But we'd like to let her know that before she
embarks upon her journey here. OK, so does our problem make enough
sense? Excellent. OK. So right. So unfortunately for us, again, it
doesn't look like a shortest path problem. And the reason is because
it's not. But rather, it's sort of a reachability problem in disguise.
And let's think about what I mean here. So right. So there's an
obvious graph here. We'll call it g out of lack of creativity.
Where what I'm going to do is give a vertex per junction.
And I'll have an undirected edge for
each pipe whose weight is the length.
OK. By the way, I think the length I didn't even mention in the problem
description. But I believe she wants to find the shortest path that
maximizes the radius. So if there are multiple different paths that
she could take that both have the same radius from the sensors,
then she'd like to be lazy and not walk too far. So
that's where this is going to come into play. OK.
That's sort of a secondary concern, I would imagine, on Agnes'
behalf here. OK. And moreover, I'm not going to even attempt
to remember the details of this problem. But rather, there's a
source, which I'm sure has some cute Hunger Games name attached to it
and some other target. And these are the two that we're going to use. And
we're going to use the same thing. And we're going to use the same thing.
And we're going to use the same thing. And these are just two nodes
in the network of pipes. And she wants a path from s to t. OK.
So first of all, let's just count and make sure that
we know. So there's a how many vertices are there?
Well, the problem actually gives a name to that.
There's order n vertices because that's just
the number of junctions, which is what we define to be n. I
forgot to write that there. And because we have a degree bound,
our favorite argument in this class, we know that
there's order n edges as well. So that's good news.
Why can't I use this graph directly? Like, let's say that I computed
the shortest path from s to t. Notice that that completely ignores
the point of the problem. The point of the problem is that Atlas
wants to avoid these starred vertices on our graph up here.
But the shortest path may not do that. In other words, she may have to
walk like a really indirect path to avoid being detected by the sensors.
That's a problem. So we need to be a little more clever than
that. We do have to think on this problem a bit. But not too much.
And so here's the basic trick. Like, let's say that let's solve a slightly
different problem first, which is let's say that I give you a radius k.
And I want to know, does there exist a path that can get me from
s to t without coming more than distance k away from the sensors?
Notice that if I have a tool that can answer that yes
or no problem. I could come up with an algorithm that
finds my number of sensors by looping over k or
something. It may not be fast enough, but I could do that.
So that problem is actually not terribly difficult.
Because essentially, what I could do conceptually
is just remove the vertices that are too close to
the sensors and then solve a reachability problem.
Like, can I get from s to t without getting distance k
away from any one of the sensors? Well, what do I do?
I just remove any vertex that's distance k away from the sensors. And then
I compute reachability. So conceptually, I think this isn't a huge leap,
intuitively speaking. But there's a lot of details to fill in.
So unraveling just a little bit more, we might define a graph gk.
And gk is going to be the subgraph of vertices whose distance with
distance bigger than k. So gk is going to be the distance k to any sensor.
And somehow, reachability in this thing can answer yes or no,
can I get from s to t without coming distance k to a sensor.
Do we know this term subgraph in this class? Essentially,
it's pretty clear what it is just from the word.
Essentially, I'm just going to remove vertices inside of
our larger graph and any edges that touch those vertices.
And obviously, if my original graph had order n, then the subgraph
has big O of n size. It might have less, but it's an upper bound.
OK, so we unravel a little bit more. Somehow, this seems like a
convenient structure, but I haven't told you how to compute it.
And in particular, the sort of annoying thing is this piece. I
need to be able to figure out if I'm distance k from any sensor.
Or more generically speaking, it might be kind of
handy to compute distance from the set of sensors
to every other vertex in my graph, every other junction in my pipe
network. OK? Well, we already covered a trick in our problem session
that's going to help us do that. Because OK, what would be a very
simple algorithm for doing that? Would be to loop over every sensor,
call Dijkstra's algorithm for each one. So that gives me the
distance to sensor number one, and the distance to sensor number two,
the distance to sensor number three. Then I take the min over
all those, and that function gives me the distance to any sensor.
That's going to be pretty easy. That's going to be a problem,
right? Because Dijkstra's algorithm runs in n log n time.
But now I've incurred another factor because I have to loop over all
the sensors. And we didn't give you a bound on how many there are.
So more generically, this is actually a problem that shows up
all the time in my everyday life, which is that we don't just
want shortest paths to a single point. Sometimes
we want shortest paths to a bunch of stuff.
Like in other words, I don't care which sensor is close to me. I don't want
to get close to any sensor. Yeah? This shows up in geometry all the time.
Maybe I want to know the closest closest, you know, like I want to find
the closest point on the highway. So the highway is driving past my house.
The highway is a whole bunch of points on some network. And I just want to
get on the highway and start driving. I don't care about the closest path
to every single point on the highway. I just want whatever is
closest to me. So this is a pretty practical thing to think about.
So how do we solve that? So let's say this is our pipe network.
I feel like I draw this network a lot. Maybe I'll spice it up.
I'll add an extra edge. OK. And maybe for board drawing purposes, these
two vertices have sensors. So I'm trying to find the shortest path distance
to either one of these two vertices from every other vertex on
the graph or vice versa. It doesn't matter. It's undirected.
And I don't want to loop over all these sensors. That's the basic
headache here. So one thing that I can do is kind of a sneaky trick.
And it's exactly the same trick that we've applied a few times in the
problem sessions here, is to add a new vertex that's kind of like a source
and make that vertex distance 0 to every one of my sensors.
And now what I'm going to do is do single source shortest path
from this new extra vertex that I added to all
the rest of my graph. Now why do I do that?
Well, if you think about it, well, there's an edge of length 0.
There's an edge of length 0. There's an edge of length 0 to any sensor.
Topologically, I can think of it like I glued all the sensors
into one vertex if I wanted. But that doesn't really matter.
In fact, that would be a different way to solve this
problem, I guess, would be to take all the sensor vertices,
glue them together into one, and then solve this problem.
But I digress. Right, so the shortest path distance
from our new source vertex to all the other ones is
going to be just the shortest path to any sensor.
Because notice that any path coming out of S necessarily has
to pass through a starred vertex. OK, so let's write that down.
Basically, what I'm trying to do here is in step one of my algorithm,
I want to label each junction with its distance to a sensor.
That's the high level goal here. And the way that I'm going to do that
is I'm going to make, oops, in the problem solution, we call it x,
so I'll be consistent. I'm going to make a function. I'm going to make
a function. I'm going to make a new vertex, or a new graph, rather,
g prime, which is equal to my original graph g, which is
coming from the pipe network with one extra vertex, which
we're going to call x, which is connected
to every motion sensor with weight 0.
OK. And now I'm going to do Dijkstra starting at x, which takes n
log n time, because I just gave you the size of our graph up here,
and gives me essentially the shortest distance to any motion
sensor from all the vertices in my graph. So that's a good thing.
That's sort of like a convenient piece of information.
But then when we're solving these kinds of
algorithms problems, notice that I've done sort
of a similar reasoning in both of the last two problems,
which you can do. And actually, it's a pretty practical way
of thinking about algorithms, where this problem tells me, at
the end of the day, my algorithm has to run n log n time, right?
Or like in the previous problem, it had to run an n cubed time, like a
v cubed time. So one thing I can do is say, what is all the information
that I can gather out of my graph in n log n time? And I might
as well compute it, right? So for instance, the distance.
The distance to the closest sensor, I just gave you an n log n
algorithm for computing it. It seems like a useful piece of information.
So what the heck? I might as well compute it in step one and
just have it around. Obviously, you could do breadth-first search
on all the computable numbers, and this might not be the most efficient
way to solve a problem. But I think for graphs, there's only so many things
that we typically want to compute. So it's worth kind of going down your
checklist. Similarly here, notice that we gave you a budget of v cubed time.
So like, you might as well. I'll compute all pairs shortest path because
we can do it in v cubed time. And why not have that information around?
It seems useful for computing radius. OK, so in any event, now in
step one, we now know how close every junction is to every sensor.
So now I can argue. I'm numbering these like steps, but they're
not really steps. These are more just like thought bubbles.
So thought bubble number two is going
to be, how do I actually construct GK?
Right? And notice I have a nice piece of information here. I now know
what vertices are inside of GK and which ones aren't because I can just
loop over all the vertices. If the distance is bigger than K, I keep it.
If it's not, I don't. Yeah, so that gives me an algorithm for computing GK.
So we can construct. Construct starts with a C. Construct
GK from our original graph G. And that's really easy.
To do just by looping over the vertices and remove
any whose distance is too big or too small, rather.
V. Does that make sense? Because those are the ones that
are dangerous. If the radius of my sensor is K, any vertex,
which this is less than or equal to K, I want to throw away. And how
much time does this take? Well, there's just a loop over the vertices.
I guess I need to account for the storage of my graph
also. But of course, this graph takes less space than G.
And so overall, this takes order n time, Tim, time and space.
But there's a catch, which is this is per K. OK? So every time.
I want to make a new GK, I incur an expensive order n. But this is
already getting us pretty close to our problem. Because what can we do?
If I have GK, I can say that BFS on GK establishes
reachability from. I can make that a few millimeters away.
So I need a 17, a 10, a 20 measure out of time. So I'll
give a 10. I can write GK off time off without error.
And if I get it wrong, then it's going to 부 After t. Right? Which is
what we care about. ish. So at the end of the day, this takes order n.
So if our problem were written slightly differently, we would
be done. If the problem said, given a radius k and a graph,
tell me yes or no, does there exist a path that stays outside of radius
k of the sensors, this is how we would do that. Hopefully, we all agree.
And we can do that in order n time.
Oh, just kidding. Order n log n time, because I had to do Dexter's
algorithm first. Thanks. OK. But sadly for us, we're not quite done,
because we want to find the largest possible k. We
want to find the biggest radius that we can stay away
from the sensors and still get successfully from s to t. So let's say
that I want to find this number. So this is going to define k star,
like at a moving target to write on, is the largest.
So I'm going to write k where gk is connected. Oh, that's not
quite right. From s to t. This is a weird way to phrase it.
Really, this should say where there
exists a path from s to t in gk. I'm sorry.
Yeah, where gk, I've just phrased this in a funny way, has path from s
to t. There we go. All right. So our question is, how do we find that?
Well, here's a dumb algorithm. I could loop over all k's,
construct gk, and then if my answer is yes is reachable,
then go to the next k, increment by 1,
and start over. So this is the dumb answer.
When I say dumb. I mean the answer that your instructor
wrote down on his notes and then realized was dumb, which
is loop over k until you get to k star, I guess plus 1,
right? Because once I get there, then I get a thumbs down.
Obviously, getting any bigger than that is only going to
make my graph smaller. This is called a filtration, right?
Because each graph is contained inside of a different one.
Actually, a filtration would be the other way. I'll think about it.
I'll think about it for later because this is not a topological data
analysis class. But in any event, if I did that, how much time will it take?
Well, remember, OK, so for one thing, I have n log n from Dijkstra's
algorithm. I don't get around that. So I always have to account for that.
But now, every time I try a new k, I incur
cost n, right? That's what we argued up here.
And so at the end of the day, this algorithm takes order k star.
And time like that. Of course, it's a little weird to have the answer of
your problem in the runtime. But k star here, we don't have any bound here.
It could be the number of vertices or anything like that. And
so if we have a budget of n log n time, this doesn't quite work.
And so the question is, can we rescue this strategy here? And the
answer, of course, is yes or else I wouldn't be standing here today.
One way that you might do that, so there's the way
that you would do that as a real algorithms person.
And there's a way you could do it by psychologically
diagnosing your instructors. Let's talk about both of those.
Let's actually do the second one first, because I think that's the most
practical if you want to get your homework done quickly. Which is as follows.
This problem tells you that you have an n log n budget of time
in order to run the algorithm. And so what does that mean?
Well, when we loop over potential g
k's that we can try, we have a budget.
Of log n tries before we're done. Yeah? So we kind of know that any
algorithm that constructs a g k and tries it can only do it log n times.
And to my knowledge, we only have one algorithm that
runs in log n time in this class, which is binary search.
And so we might be thinking very critically about how we
could use that tool. But more generally than that, I think
this is actually a strategy that shows up a lot both in algorithms and
actually in numerical analysis a lot. Which is you have some like yes or no,
answer and you want to find the point on the interface where yes flips
to no. And so one way to do it is to sort of bound it on two ends,
then keep dividing in half. And as long as your relationship is a bunch of
yeses and then a bunch of nos, you can keep doing that by binary search.
So let's think about it this way. So we have a long interval of
k values. By the way, obviously, there's an upper bound here,
which is like the biggest distance to any vertex in my graph or
something like that. Yeah, like the sum of all distances or some.
That would be a very large number compared to that. But you can afford a
lot. You could, if you took the sum of every edge, here's a way to do it.
If you took this to be the sum of every possible edge length. It
might not be bounded in n, polynomial. Polynomially bounded in n.
Difference between u and n.
Sure. So very large numbers in the year. Space. OK.
I'm not sure that that's quite right. But that's OK.
In any event, let's say that we have an upper bound for k for now.
Then what do we know? We know that here's the k star that I want.
And to the left, my algorithm will return yes. This algorithm up here.
Up here, it'll say no. So one thing I can do, one thing I should do,
is put k star, not right at the center of my interval, for illustration
purposes. But now I can binary search, because I could query here.
And now I'm going to get a no. And maybe I subdivide. That's the midpoint
for some reason. Now I get a yes. And I can triangulate in on what I want.
Right? So that's our basic strategy, is binary search
here. But we have to figure out how to do that exactly. OK.
So first of all, there is an obvious upper bound here, which is just
the biggest distance from any vertex to any sensor. Yeah. Right.
So we could probably do that. We could probably come up with a conservative
one if we didn't feel like it. But conveniently, in step one, remember
that computing convenient numbers is always a convenient
thing to do. Clearly, if Katniss wants to, sorry, sorry,
Atniss wants to go within a radius that's bigger than the
distance of any vertex to any sensor, she's in trouble.
Because that covers the entire graph. Yeah? So right. So we actually
do have an upper bound here, which is the biggest distance to a sensor.
And now we want a binary search. But we have to be a little bit
careful how to do it, because we want to be logarithmic in n, which
is like the number of vertices in our graph. And of
course, the way that I've drawn this interval here,
as Jason points out, I don't at least immediately have a bound on this
number in terms of n. It could be that my edge weights are really ginormous.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. OK. So right. So how can we
get around that? Well, essentially, what we want to be doing
is binary search in an array that scales like the
vertices. OK? And here's the solution that I came up with,
which I'm pretty sure is the same as the one in the answer.
I should really check that before teaching this thing,
which is to do the following, which is a. Remember, again, we have a budget
at n log n. And so we can do a constant number of things that take n log
n time. We just might as well keep doing it. Yeah. And so another kind
of convenient thing we might do is sort my vertices by the distance
to x, which of course, remember, is exactly the
distance to their closest sensor. Why would you do that?
Well, in some sense, as I move along that array, that's the sort
of order in which I'm going to remove vertices from my graph
and make the radius get bigger and bigger and bigger. Does that make
sense? Because the first couple ones are the ones right next to the sensor.
As I move along this array, they get farther and farther away.
OK? So we're going to say, and of course, why can we do that?
Because sorting, I think this is one that all computer science students
everywhere know, takes n log n time using whatever your favorite sorting.
Well, that's not true. Whatever my favorite sorting algorithm is. OK. And
we're going to take d i to be the distance, the i-th largest, d i. OK.
Actually, I think in my notes I got this wrong. The i-th smallest, I'm
diverging from my notes. So there is a high likelihood of a sign mistake
that's about to happen. OK. And now what I'm going to do is I'm going to
binary search on i. In other words, on the index into my distance array.
Is there a reason to do that? Is there a reason? Like,
let's say that. My distances are like 1, 2, 5, 7.
So these are the distance of some vertex to a sensor. And
let's say that I test 3. And I notice that 3 is admissible.
In other words, she can get from one vertex to another, never
getting within a radius of 3. Should I try a radius of 4?
Well, no, because I'm going to remove vertices
only when I pass an element in this array.
So it makes sense to do binary search not in distance space, but rather
in array index space. Because those are the sort of place junctures
that determine when I'm going to remove stuff. OK. So right.
So remember, how big is this array? It's got length n.
So overall, this binary search takes log n time. And that's good
because our whole algorithm now, what do we do? We binary search on d.
Or rather, we binary search on i. And then we take di and plug it into
our algorithm up there, too. We construct our subgraph. We test yes or no.
And that tells us the left or the right interval in our binary
search. And we recurse. And so overall, this takes log n time.
But rather, log n steps of binary search. And of course, each one of
these steps, as I argued up there, takes order n time. So overall.
Our algorithm takes order n log. Oh no, I made an accidental
theta. n log n time. And that was the bound we wanted to achieve.
As usual, there's a lot of detritus that we need to clean up at the end of
our problem here. One of them is that we actually want to return a path.
But that's not so bad. So now we've essentially determined
that we can compute k star in n log n time. Well, that's good.
So now we actually want the path. We can. Construct. Construct our
graph one more time right at k star. I suppose we already have it around
from the end of binary search. And then use whatever your favorite
reachability algorithm is to go from s to t and give Katniss the path
that she wants. Or specifically, Dijkstra's algorithm if you want the
shortest path. Which is courteous because she doesn't want to walk too far.
She doesn't have to. Moreover, let's see. There are a couple of
boundary cases that are probably worth mentioning in your problem.
So for instance, if k star equals 0, in other words, I do my binary
search. I get all the way back to the first element of my array.
And it's still saying I can't do it. What does that mean?
That means that I cannot go from my source to my target node
without passing through a vertex that has a sensor at it. Yep.
And in which case, what do you do? Well, you can return any path.
Or you might as well return the shortest path so that she
can run. OK. And that, I believe, concludes our problem.
Any questions about that one? Thumbs up. Cool. How are we
doing on time? As usual, I think I'm going to end early.
And we're at precisely the same time I've always had at problem four.
OK. So problem four, we move from one fictional universe to another here.
So now we're playing like OK Pond or something like that.
Sorry, if I didn't write so big, I wouldn't have
to waste half of class erasing. But that's OK.
Right.
Cool. So now we have Ashley Gidham. And Ashley Gidham
is trying to go from Twinkle Town to Blue Bluff.
And these are both two clearings in the Tenko region. I'm sure if I
played Pokemon, this would have meaning to me. Or whatever this is.
But in any case, I'm going to go with this. OK. So in any event, we have
a map of a bunch of clearings. Not liking the erasing on this board.
So maybe we'll start up here.
OK. So we have n clearings.
And they're connected by two-way trails.
And thankfully, there's a map. There's less than or
equal to five trails connecting in every clearing.
This is like our favorite detail to add to 6.006 problems, is the
degree bound. Yeah. OK. Now with every trail, we associate a length,
which we're going to call L sub t for a trail t. But in addition to
that, we're going to have another piece of information, which is that it
has a set of critical points. So we're going to have critters on a c
sub t. So now every trail, our character here is walking along the path.
And what does she want to do? Any time that she walks along a path,
she collects a critter. Or however many critters are on that path.
In fact, she feels a very similar way to how I feel at TJ Maxx.
She's walking down the aisles, and she can't help herself.
She's got to catch every critter that she goes past on the
path. There's no option here. She can't leave it behind.
Because if she does, then she'll be sad. And the reason why
our character might not be able to pick up one of the critters
would be if she ran out of her tools for picking up these critters,
which are apparently pocket spheres. And she has k spheres.
In other words, she has a backpack. And the backpack can hold
that many spheres at a time. OK. There are a few details here.
One is that every time she walks along a path, she collects
all the critters. But then if she walks down that path again,
she'll collect the same set of critters. Apparently,
they respawn. They're very prolific, these critters.
And moreover, there are stores at some of the clearings.
And at these stores, she can get rid of the critters she currently
has and drop them off and pick up empty spheres. Instead.
So essentially, every time she does that, she empties her backpack and
gets a new set of material where she can keep picking up the critters.
I have many questions about this character. Does she just leave them there?
Does she come back for them later? What does she do with the critters?
There's a lot of questions. Does she have a bigger bag she can go
back around to the store? But in this fictional universe, we're
not going to worry about these problems. OK. And so essentially, the
question here, is that there are two locations. I don't remember the name.
Trundle Trown to Blue Bluff. But she's trying to travel in between.
And she gets sad if she comes across a critter that she can't collect.
So the question is, can you find the shortest path without
being sad? And in kind of a da-da twist in this problem,
if no such path exists, in other words, it's like she has to walk
along some long trail with a bunch of critters, more than k critters,
I guess, in the worst case, then sadness is unavoidable, is what your
code is apparently supposed to return, which is really defeatist.
I don't know who wrote this problem set. OK. The question is, how
do we solve this? OK. So it looks like a shortest path problem.
But as with all problems in 6.006, there's a slight twist,
right? In this case, the twist is that it's the shortest path
without becoming sad, where sadness means that
you ran out of spheres to collect your critters.
Now, notice that we're given a budget, by the way, of, I
believe, nk log nk times. Is that right? Like that. OK.
Notice that this is a little suspicious. Somehow, it makes us think
that the size of our problem really is nk rather than just n or k. OK.
So how could we do this? Let's think back to a problem that we solved
yesterday under the assumption that you guys are binge watching your 6.006
problem sessions here. And remember, the problem
yesterday, we had this dude that was walking along paths.
And every third path, he had to drink a beer. And he had to drink
a beer. And he had to drink a beer. And he had to drink a beer.
And he had to drink a beer. I've tried this on my commute home. And it
doesn't work terribly well. But in any event, we have a similar scenario
here, where there's some number that we need to keep
track of. In this case, it's the number of critters
that our character has remaining that she can pick up. So she starts with
an empty bag. As she collects them, the amount of capacity in her bag
decreases until she gets to a store. And then it goes back again. But the
good news is that our runtime bound includes k in it. So it's actually OK.
To make an algorithm that scales in the number of critters that she can
carry around. It's kind of atypical, but an interesting choice here.
So remember, the term I introduced last time for this kind of universe is
that it's kind of a state machine. In addition to walking along the graph,
she needs to know how much capacity she has for critters. And so
here's a way to do it. So I think actually this problem isn't too bad,
given that you saw the problem where you do every third vertex in our
last problem. Session somehow it's just like a same church, different pew
kind of scenario here. So in this case, one thing we can do
is we're going to make a graph. We're going to call it g.
It's got vertices v, edges e, just for fun. But what we're
going to do is have k plus 1 vertices for every clearing.
And the reason is that what we're going to do is we're going
to walk along the graph. And as we traverse our edges, we're
not only going to keep track of the costs, like the distance that
she's walking, but also the number of critters that she has remaining
in her bag that she can store. And the way that we can
do that is by keeping a bunch of copies of our graph
and ascending every time that we collect a new critter. Does
that make sense? OK, so let's add a little bit more detail here.
So in particular, I can define v, c, i is going to be the vertex
per clearing comma critter space. And the way that I can view it is
that this is sort of representing that I'm at clearing, oops,
this should be a c. And I have i pocket spheres that are empty.
So initially, I'm going to start at v, s comma 0 and go from there. OK?
K. I guess it depends whether you're decreasing it or increasing it.
And t pocket spheres is i. Oh, you're right. Yeah, I'm sorry. So in that
case, I guess it would be k. We'll see if I manage to do that consistently
throughout my answer here. OK, so now I need to tell you how
to make the edges in our graph. And so let's do that next.
So in particular, for our graph, we're going to do this. OK. OK. So
we're all trails between a and b with length l. And critter c, right?
So she picks up c critters. She traverses distance l. She gets
from a to b or vice versa. And our trails are bidirectional here.
We need to define edges.
And they look like this. So we sort of have two different cases.
One is where you have a store. And one is when you don't, right?
Because that's going to affect how your state changes.
Right, so the first one would be, oh, did I get this whole thing
backward? Oh, don't tell me that. No, I did. OK, good. Great.
So the first case would be a does not have a store.
Right, so in this case, she leaves with the same number of critters
she had in her bag minus whatever critters she picks up along the way.
Right, so now I'm going to have an edge of length. L.
And I'm going to go from v, a, i to v, b, i minus c.
Right, so the idea is that I go from a to b. And in the process, I
lose c critters. Right, but I have to do this for all the possible i's
that I could see in my state. So that
goes from ct. Right. To k. Oops. To k.
C. Associated with the trail t, which I decided not to use. OK, right,
so the basic point here is that there are a bunch of different states
where I can traverse this trail. But I have to have at least c critters in
my bag if I'm allowed to traverse this trail, or else I will be sad. OK?
And so I kind of copy this edge a bunch of different times
to represent all the possible transitions I can make.
And similarly, let's say that a does have a store.
Well, I still want to add an edge, but now I have the luxury of
clearing out all the stuff in my bag before collecting the critters.
Yeah, so now I still want an edge of length l. But now I get to
connect more vertices and reset my state in the process. Right.
So now I'm going to go from v a comma i to v b. And where am I
going to end up? Well, how many critters are going to be in my bag?
I have a bag of capacity k. And I just traversed the edge from a
to b, which contains c critters. So I get an v k minus c like that.
And of course, I can't do this. I can do that
for all i from oh, yeah. I have to be careful.
Well, no. Actually, just for all i is fine. Yeah. I think there might
be a mistake in how I copied it down or a mistake in the problem.
A mistake in the problem. You still need? Yeah, I think this is right.
Yeah. So I think there's. we wrote for all i. And some interval.
But we didn't have to. OK. Right. So those are our different
cases. So essentially, in this case, we clear out our q here.
Well, not even a q, just our set of spheres. We reset. We
go back here. Notice that the second vertex doesn't even
have an i in its index because it doesn't matter.
OK. And then similarly, so that gets me from a to b.
I also have to do the symmetric thing to go from b to a.
OK. So now I have a graph. And first of all, we should reason and make sure
that we can actually construct this graph in a reasonable amount of time.
So let's do that really fast.
Right. So the number of vertices in our graph, well, we're going to
have to do that. OK. Well, I basically have k plus 1 copies of my graph.
So it's equal to k plus 1 times n. That's good. So that's
order k n space, I suppose. And similarly, there's k edges that
are associated with every trail. And there's order n trails
because I have a degree bound. So overall, there's order k n edges.
And I have a degree bound in my graph. OK. Great. So now my problem is
not so bad. I have a source, which is the place where our walker starts.
I have t, which is the destination where she wants to go. So what
do I need? Well, I just need any path that starts at vsk. Right.
In other words, she starts it at. s and has a full bag
with k capacity and ends up at 2v t, i for any i, right?
Because it doesn't matter how much capacity she has in her
bag when she meets her destination. So this is for all i.
Any path avoids sadness in the way this problem is written. Right.
So how could I do that? Well, she wants the shortest path. Right.
So I can do that. So I can just do Dijkstra's
algorithm from vsk. And do a bit of cleanup afterward
to check all the different i's and find this
closest one. And how much time does that take?
Well, my graph takes k n space because it has k n vertices and order
k n edges. So overall, this is going to take order k n log k n time.
Which is a good thing because that's exactly the problem I asked for.
And of course, if the shortest path is infinity, then what do we know?
Can you say it with me?
Sadness is unavoidable.
Which is a weird thing to write on a blackboard. OK. And
so that's our problem. That's our basic problem here.
So what was our strategy if we step back 10 feet? Essentially,
we took our graph. And rather than just making our graph,
we made k copies of it with edges that kind of point upstairs,
meaning that you give away spheres in the process of traversing
these different edges, except when you hit the stores, which
brings you back to level 0. So that was our basic graph structure.
And then we just need to do shortest path on that thing. Any
questions about that? Yes. Last time we did graph duplication,
we made a layered graph. And you kept making these transitions.
And it was a DAG. So can't we do this in linear time?
Can't we do this in linear time? So in other words,
why is our graph not a DAG in this particular case?
Let me think about that for a second.
There's nothing about this problem that says that the graph has to be a
DAG. In particular, I guess you could keep walking. If you had a path. Yeah.
With a store that were exactly the same as the number of
critters, you could keep walking back and forth along that path.
And so there's a little cycle there, which would be enough to not
be able to do it in linear time. Well, the edges that we constructed
don't necessarily correspond to the edges in the original
trails. That's not the problem. Sure. That's absolutely right.
So we constructed a directed graph out of our original one. But that
directed graph also can contain cycles. Right? So yeah. So I think.
I'm giving you work. So I have a graph with two vertices. Maybe there's
other graph stuff going on. But whatever. I have two vertices here.
And I have some number of critters here. And I have a store on
either end of my edge just because I'm boring and conservative.
And now, well, assuming that c is less than k, I can just keep going back
and forth along this edge as many times I want. And this is for free.
Right? Because every time I get to the end of the edge, I throw
all my critters away. So that's an example of a cycle in my graph.
And because there's a cycle, I'm not in the DAG case anymore.
So it's a cycle in the constructed graph. Sorry. Yeah.
It is a cycle here and also a cycle in the constructed
graph. Yeah. Sorry. I guess that's true. All right.
Any other questions I can make a hash of here? Excellent. So am I out
of time? Ah, shucks. No. OK. In that case, we'll do the last problem.
Actually, the last problem I think is the most interesting
one. So as usual, I've left myself with not enough time. OK.
Which of these boards is the tidiest? The answer is none
of the above. So let's use the backs here. OK. Right.
So our last problem is a shipping problem, not a transshipment
problem, which happens to be my area of research, but rather just
a good old shipping thing. So here, strangely, I did not
give myself my complete notes. So this will be fun. Right.
So I'm trying to ship servers from San Francisco to Cambridge
by truck. And I have all these bunch of third party companies
that all have pairs of cities that they can ship between and only so
much. These companies are kind of divas. They have a weight limit.
They only have cities. They're directed edges. I can't
like, they don't drive their trucks back apparently.
Or maybe they pick up somebody else's stuff and they're just
picking your stuff up in the boring direction or whatever.
So I have a bunch of n trucking routes.
And each route, r sub i, is a tuple with si, ti, w, i, ci.
And what are all these things? So here, this is the source.
This is the target of every shipping route, every trucking route
here. This is the target. So this is where the truck starts.
This is where the truck ends. This is the max weight that the truck can
handle. So the truck only has so much space in it. The tires are only so big.
If I put something of weight bigger than w, then my truck is going to die.
So that's the most that I can put on this truck. And this is the cost.
And I have n routes that look like this. And I'm trying to ship
servers. And of course, some of my servers are too darn busy.
But we make an assumption here, which is that our trucking routes form
a continuous network. I can get from s to t and ship at the very least
like a pencil eraser, like some minimal amount of
weight. And so the basic endpoint of this problem
is going to be to sort of figure out the heaviest thing that
I can ship. And we give you a problem on the path toward that
to help prove a little bit about this. This is a very typical kind
of setup. So again, I've got a bunch of trucking routes, each one of
which has a max weight. And I'm going to want to know, first
of all, what's the maximum amount of weight I can ship?
And then what is the minimum cost I can ship that weight?
So in problem A, which is marked as useful digression,
we're first going to prove kind of a handy, but not really a handy
inequality. I decided to go off book with my proof ever so slightly of this.
So get excited for this to be slightly wrong
in a subtle way, which is what I specialize in.
But in particular, we're going to make a definition here. So let's
say that pi is a weighted path. OK? Then the bottleneck of pi.
And pi is going to be the minimum
edge weight of any edge in pi.
And to make sure that we see how this is connected
to the problem, if I'm trying to ship a server and I
have to put it on truck 1 and truck 2 and truck 3 and
truck 4 and truck 5, obviously of those five trucks,
the one whose capacity for weight is this small, OK? The smallest is the
only one that matters in terms of the heaviest thing that I can ship. OK.
So right now, given a directed graph and two vertices s
and t, we're going to define a quantity called b of s, t.
And we're going to say that this is the max
over any path pi from s to t of the bottleneck.
And we're going to say that this is the max over any path
pi of pi. OK? So the sanity, check this quantity here.
Essentially what it's saying is at the end of the day, I have this big
network of trucking routes. I just want to go from one city to another.
And I don't care which series of trucks I want to use. I
just want to maximize the weight that I could ship. Right?
And so this is saying I'm going to look at
all the different paths that I could take.
Each path is band limited by the one truck
that has the lightest weight that it can carry.
And I'm going to find the path that has the lightest weight.
That has the best bottleneck as measured by this quantity.
Using the word best because I tend to make sign mistakes.
That's a vague term. OK. And then, right. So writing too big.
Hopefully, I won't run out of space. We're going to make one additional
definition, which is i of t is the incoming neighbors of t. OK.
And then the problem is asking you to prove a particular inequality
here. Claim, which is that b of st is bigger than or equal to the min
of two values, b of sv or w of vt for all vt.
So I'm going to write this as a So let's see what this
is saying. So remember that this is like the capacity
that I can ship from s to t using any root. And that upper bounds the
minimum of two things. Either the capacity of shipping to one of my neighbors
with an incoming edge or the weight of basically shipping from that
neighbor to me. Notice this is kind of similar to a triangle inequality,
which is why we're going to kind of know how to
solve part b of this problem pretty easily. OK.
And moreover, with equality for some v star in i of t. OK. Guess
what that v star is going to be. It's going to be the vertex that's
sort of the previous one on the path of trucks that I actually
take to ship stuff. Right? OK. So how can we prove this?
So the intuition here is that the path that's actually giving you this
bottleneck, this bs comma t, has to include one of my incoming edges.
And I'm just trying to find it. That's roughly what's going
on in this inequality. And by the way, whenever a problem
asks you to prove an inequality, you should step back. I
feel like I spend like 85% of my day with research students
sort of saying like, OK, but what is it really telling me about life? And
this is a good. Example. OK. So to that end, I'm going to make a definition
which I found to be convenient when I was solving this problem,
which is the following. I'm going to say that pi s comma t
is going to be the actual path that gives me the bottleneck. So this is
kind of like the arg max over all pi. I'm going to use really bad notation.
Pi is the connect s to t. That's how we're
going to think of that. Of the bottleneck.
So in other words, this is the path that actually realizes this
quantity b. So in other words, b of s t is equal to bottleneck.
Pi only has two lines. This is convenient for me
because the reasoning about that path makes some sense.
OK. So now we're going to prove the inequality first. And then we may
or may not choose prove the equality case depending on how I feel. OK.
So right. So let's section this off and try and use my
board a little more conservatively here. OK. So right.
So now let's take the vertex v from the incoming edges here.
OK. OK. So right. So now we have a path that goes from s to t,
and we're going to call this the bin of t, right? Because that's what we
need to prove this. And we're going to prove the inequality directly here.
In particular, we can define a path that goes from s to t as
follows. I could take the pi s v, and then concatenate onto the end
of this guy, t. Right? Because we know that it's going to be a
lot of time. Right? Right. OK. Right. OK. OK. OK. OK. OK. OK.
that there's a directed edge from v to t by definition of
what this i is. OK? Right. And so this is kind of convenient
because this is like the bottleneck path for one of my
neighbors. And now I'm just kind of sticking an edge on there.
And we know that, of course, this is a candidate path to get from s to t.
But it may not be the one that actually achieves the bottleneck. OK? Right.
So yeah. And let's define that to be pi. It's a twiddle just
for fun. I like to give things names. OK. So what do we know?
We know that b of s comma t, well, this by definition is the max bottleneck
of any incoming path going from s to t. This is a path from s to t. Yeah?
So because this is the max, it is bigger than or equal to. Or equal
to bottleneck of pi twiddle. Right? That's the nice thing about maxes.
They tend to be bigger than other stuff. OK. Well, what is the bottleneck
of pi twiddle? Well, remember our definition of bottleneck here. Right?
It's the min edge weight over my entire path. Well, I have two options.
Either that edge weight is the edge from v to t, or it's the edge weight.
That's associated to the rest of this stuff. Yeah? So either this is
the min of the bottleneck of the first segment of our path, pi sv.
By the way, that may be empty. And that's like, OK. That's just
like a one edge path. You can dispense with that case pretty easily.
Or the weight of vt. Cool? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. By
definition, bottleneck of pi sv is exactly this quantity. Right?
Because that's what I chose it to be over here. Yeah? So this is
exactly min of bs comma v. That was supposed to be a v, but I wrote a t.
Or w of v comma t. And that is exactly what we wanted to prove. Yeah? So
that takes care of our inequality case. Do I want to do the equality case?
I don't think I do. Yeah. So it's not too hard to check the equality
case. Essentially, you can make a pretty easy contradiction. Right?
Because if it's strictly larger, then what does that mean?
That means that every single incoming edge, none of them
can be the edge where your bottleneck path comes in.
And obviously, there's something wrong with that. OK.
So I'll refer you guys to the notes for that one. And finally,
the problem says, assuming that, oh, I'm going to do this.
So now we have kind of a funny constant in here,
just to make your life a little bit annoying.
We have, at most, three square root n cities that
we care about. Again, why three? Why not, I think.
And what we want is the weight of the single largest server and the minimum
cost to ship that thing. So we want one, the largest weight we can ship.
And we'll call that w star to ship. And two is the smallest cost to
ship that weight, w star. OK? So let's do two first, because it's easy.
So let's say that I was able to compute w star. So now what? What
can I do? Well, I can construct a graph where I only keep around
the trucks that can ship at least this amount of weight, because
the other ships are, I really want them to be boats in this problem.
But the other trucks are useless. If they can't cover w star, then they're
not pulling their weight. Yeah? So to do part two here, what can I do?
I can make a new graph g. So c with a vertex for every city and
an edge, a directed edge, sorry, per shipping route with, this
is going to be an unfortunate class. I'm going to say,
edge weight to refer to the edge weight in my graph.
And that's going to be equal to the cost of the edge.
And only keep around, but only for routes that
can carry at least w star amount of weight.
And now what do we do? Well, it's the shortest path. At this point,
shortest path, which is really the minimum cost in this case,
because that's what we're associating to the edges, is
going to give me the cost of shipping w star in my network.
I think that's pretty obvious from this construction. So that's Dijkstra,
D-I-J-K-S-T-R-A. And now the only question is, how much time does it take?
So let's say that I do the brain dead version of Dijkstra,
where I just use a direct access array to do my priority queue.
So if you recall, that'll take big O of mod v cubed here, squared,
squared. Yep, you're right. Sorry. I was thinking Johnson's algorithm. OK.
Well, in this case, how big is v? Well, it's square root of n, 3 times
square root of n at most. So of course, v squared is really big O of n.
And that part is solved. So really, our only remaining problem
here is to do part one. And I don't have nearly enough time.
In fact, I'm completely out of time. So maybe we'll just talk through it
really briefly. Sorry about that. Essentially, the basic observation here
is that the inequality that we proved in part A of our problem is kind
of like the triangle inequality of the bottleneck world in some sense.
Essentially, what it's giving you is some, or update formula that looks
kind of like the update formula that we'd apply in Dijkstra's algorithm
for shortest path. The basic assumption here being that, well, my shortest
path has to come from somewhere. So if I look over all of my neighbors,
and then I kind of add in my closest edge, or rather,
the sum of the path length to the previous vertex
plus the edge to me, it gives the shortest path to me. Here, instead
of that, we're saying the biggest bottleneck path. So what do I do?
I look at all of my incoming neighbors. I find the one with the biggest
bottleneck, which is band limited by their bottleneck plus the bottleneck
of the incoming edge. And then I update myself. The only thing
remaining here is to basically do exactly Dijkstra's algorithm.
But rather than updating by summing edge length, we update by using
this formula. And essentially, everything else remains the same.
So conveniently, I've run out of time. So I won't even have to
jumble this one on the board. I'll let you guys do that one at home.
But I actually think the explanation of the written material is
pretty self-evident for this problem. So that's probably just as well.